O'Reily ZeroMQ 2013
Page 366 (386/515)

The Lazy Perfectionist
Never design anything that’s not a precise, minimal answer to a problem we can identify
and have to solve.
The Lazy Perfectionist spends his idle time observing others and identifying problems
that are worth solving. He looks for agreement on those problems, always asking, “What
is the real problem?” Then he moves, precisely and minimally, to build (or get others
to build) a usable answer to one problem. He uses, or gets others to use, those solutions.
And he repeats this until there are no problems left to solve, or time or money runs out.
The Benevolent Tyrant
The control of a large force is the same principle as the control of a few men: it is merely
a question of dividing up their numbers. — Sun Tzu
The Benevolent Tyrant divides large problems into smaller ones and throws them at
groups to focus on. He brokers contracts between these groups, in the form of APIs and
the “unprotocols” we’ll read about in the next chapter. The Benevolent Tyrant constructs
a supply chain that starts with problems and results in usable solutions. He is ruthless
about how the supply chain works, but does not tell people what to work on, or how to
do their work.
The Earth and Sky
The ideal team consists of two sides: one writing code, and one providing feedback.
The Earth and Sky work together as a whole, in close proximity, but they communicate
formally through issue tracking. Sky seeks out problems from others and from personal
use of the product and feeds these to Earth. Earth rapidly answers with testable solutions.
Earth and Sky can work through dozens of issues in a day. Sky talks to other users, and
Earth talks to other developers. Earth and Sky may be two people, or two small groups.
366  |  Chapter 6: The ØMQ Community
The Open Door
The accuracy of knowledge comes from diversity.
The Open Door accepts contributions from almost anyone. She does not argue quality
or direction, instead allowing others to argue that and to get more engaged. She calcu‐
lates that even a troll will bring more diverse opinions to the group. She lets the group
form its opinion about what goes into stable code, and she enforces this opinion with
the help of a Benevolent Tyrant.
The Laughing Clown
Perfection precludes participation.
The Laughing Clown, often acting as the Happy Failure, makes no claim to high com‐
petence. Instead, his antics and bumbling attempts provoke others into rescuing him
from his own tragedy. Somehow, however, he always identifies the right problems to
solve. People are so busy proving him wrong, they don’t realize they’re doing valuable
work.
The Mindful General
Make no plans. Set goals, develop strategies and tactics.
The Mindful General operates in unknown territory, solving problems that are hidden
until they are nearby. Thus he makes no plans, but seeks opportunities, then exploits
them rapidly and accurately. He develops tactics and strategies in the field, and teaches
these to his men so they can move independently, and together.
The Social Engineer
If you know the enemy and know yourself, you need not fear the result of a hundred
battles. — Sun Tzu
The Social Engineer reads the hearts and minds of those she works with and for. She
asks of everyone, “What makes this person angry, insecure, argumentative, calm, hap‐
py?” She studies their moods and dispositions. With this knowledge she can encourage
those who are useful, and discourage those who are not. The Social Engineer never acts
on her own emotions.
The Constant Gardener
He will win whose army is animated by the same spirit throughout all its ranks. — Sun
Tzu
The Constant Gardener grows a process from a small seed, step-by-step, as more people
come into the project. He makes every change for a precise reason, with agreement from
Patterns for Success  |  367
everyone. He never imposes a process from above, but lets others come to consensus,
and then he enforces that consensus. In this way, everyone owns the process together,
and by owning it, they are attached to it.
The Rolling Stone
After crossing a river, you should get far away from it. — Sun Tzu
The Rolling Stone accepts her own mortality and transience. She has no attachment to
her past work. She accepts that all that we make is destined for the trash can; it is just a
matter of time. With precise, minimal investments, she can move rapidly away from the
past and stay focused on the present and near future. Above all, she has no ego and no
pride to be hurt by the actions of others.
The Pirate Gang
Code, like all knowledge, works best as collective—not private—property.
The Pirate Gang organizes freely around problems. It accepts authority insofar as au‐
thority provides goals and resources. The Pirate Gang owns and shares all it makes:
every work is fully remixable by others in the Pirate Gang. The gang moves rapidly as
new problems emerge, and it is quick to abandon old solutions if those stop being
relevant. No persons or groups can monopolize any part of the supply chain.
The Flash Mob
Water shapes its course according to the nature of the ground over which it flows. — Sun
Tzu
The Flash Mob comes together in space and time as needed, then disperses as soon as
it can. Physical closeness is essential for high-bandwidth communications, but over time
it creates technical ghettos, where Earth gets separated from Sky. The Flash Mob tends
to collect a lot of frequent flier miles.
The Canary Watcher
Pain is not, generally, a Good Sign.
The Canary Watcher measures the quality of an organization by his own pain level, and
the observed pain levels of those with whom he works. He brings new participants into
existing organizations so they can express the raw pain of the innocent. He may use
alcohol to get others to verbalize their pain points. He asks others, and himself, “Are
you happy in this process, and if not, why not?” When an organization causes pain in
himself or others, he treats that as a problem to be fixed. People should feel joy in their
work.
368  |  Chapter 6: The ØMQ Community
The Hangman
Never interrupt others when they are making mistakes.
The Hangman knows that we learn only by making mistakes, and he gives others copious
rope with which to learn. He only pulls the rope gently, when it’s time. A little tug to
remind the other of her precarious position. Allowing others to learn by failure gives
the good reason to stay, and the bad an excuse to leave. The Hangman is endlessly patient,
because there is no shortcut to the learning process.
The Historian
Keeping the public record may be tedious, but it’s the only way to prevent collusion.
The Historian forces discussion into the public view, to prevent collusion to own areas
of work. The Pirate Gang depends on full and equal communications that do not depend
on momentary presence. No one really reads the archives, but the simple possibility
stops most abuses. The Historian encourages the right tool for the job: email for tran‐
sient discussions, IRC for chatter, wikis for knowledge, issue tracking for recording
opportunities.
The Provocateur
When a man knows he is to be hanged in a fortnight, it concentrates his mind wonder‐
fully. — Samuel Johnson
The Provocateur creates deadlines, enemies, and the occasional impossibility. Teams
work best when they don’t have time for the crap. Deadlines bring people together and
focus the collective mind. An external enemy can move a passive team into action. The
Provocateur never takes the deadline too seriously. The product is always ready to ship.
But she gently reminds the team of the stakes: fail, and we all look for other jobs.
The Mystic
When people argue or complain, just write them a Sun Tzu quotation. — Mikko Kop‐
panen
The Mystic never argues directly. He knows that to argue with an emotional person only
creates more emotion. Instead, he sidesteps the discussion. It’s hard to be angry at a
Chinese general, especially when he has been dead for 2,400 years. The Mystic plays
Hangman when people insist on the right to get it wrong.